Inventory of the John P. McKnight papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John P. McKnight papers
1924-1945
81140
McKnight, John P.
2 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize file (0.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains reports, notes, orders, proclamations, and photographs, relating to American military operations in Italy and France during World War II, and especially to activities of the Fifth Corps (V Corps) in Normandy following the D-Day landings.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1929 AB degree
1931 Earned LL.B degree, University of Nebraska
1931-1941 Engaged in general practice of law and owning and running a business
1941 Entered U.S. Army as reserve officer
1943 Engaged in combat as War Department representative with Fifth Army for invasion landing at Salerno, Italy
1944 Engaged in combat as War Department representative with First Army for invasion of France and Normandy campaign
Scope and Content of Collection
The John P. McKnight papers consist of reports, notes, orders, proclamations, and photographs, relating to American military operations in Italy and France during World War II, and especially to activities of the Fifth Corps (V Corps) in Normandy following the D-Day landings. The collection presents documents relating to organization and performance of the United States Army Fifth (V) Corps as well as some information about McKnight's personal life.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
United States. Army. Corps, V.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Italy.
Collection Contents
- Personal file and collected documents, 1924-1944, undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical data, undated (Folder 1: 1)
  - Diary, undated (Folder 1: 2)
  - Notes, undated (Folder 1: 3)
  - Printed matter, 1924-1944 (Folder 1: 4)
    Booklets in French and German
  - Miscellany, undated (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes decontamination data card, label, notes, registration card, and travel schedule
- U.S. Army records and related materials, 1924, 1942-1945, undated (Box 1)
  - Citation for Legion of Merit for "exceptionally meritorious conduct in the performance of outstanding services in the Operations Division, War Department General Staff, from November 1942" April 1945,?, undated (Folder 1: 6)
  - Participation in Unit Gas Officers Course about map exercise tactics, 1942 January-February (Folder 1: 7)
  - U.S. Army V Corps, 1924, 1944-1945, undated (Folder 1)
    - General, 1924, 1942-1945, undated (Folder 1)
      - General, 1944 and undated (Folder 1: 8)
      - Clippings, 1924 (Folder 1: 9)
      - List, undated (Folder 1: 10)
      - Max Katzowitz interview, 1944 (Folder 1: 11)
      - Memoranda, 1944-1945 (Folder 1: 12)
      - Reports, 1944 and undated (Folder 1: 13)
    - Army Post Office (APO) 230, 1944 (Folder 1)
      - General, 1944 (Folder 1: 14)
      - Circulars and memoranda, 1944 (Folder 1: 15)
    - APO 305, 1944, undated (Folder 1)
      - General, 1944, undated (Folder 1: 16)
      - Civil Affairs Section, 1944, undated (Folder 1)
        - General documents, 1944, undated (Folder 1: 17)
        - Memoranda, 1944 (Folder 1: 18)
      - War Department, undated (Folder 1)
        - Clippings, extracts from War Department manual, informational material on the Glider Program, list of shipping ticket, memoranda, plan for action, and schedule, undated (Folder 1: 19)
    - APO 306 Memoranda, 1943 (Folder 1: 20)
    - APO 307 Field order and memoranda, 1942 (Folder 1: 21)
  - U.S. Army VI Corps, 1943, undated (Folder 1)
    - "General information and of information to be secured by staff officers visiting front,", 1943 (Folder 1: 22)
    - Report, undated (Folder 1: 23)
    - Telephone message from G3 45th Division to G3 6th Corps regarding bombing resulting in burning three trucks and death of one person, 1943 (Folder 1: 24)
- Photographs, 1944, undated (Box 2)
  Arranged by format
  - Negatives, undated (Folder 2)
    - Unidentified, undated (Folder 2: 1)
      Includes negatives of election posters and unidentified individuals in home environment and war scenes
    - Unidentified individuals in home environment, undated (Folder 2: 2)
    - War scenes, undated (Folder 2: 3)
    - Election posters, undated (Folder 2: 4)
    - Unidentified individuals, animals, and sea in the background, undated (Folder 2: 5)
    - Churches and buildings, undated (Folder 2: 6)
    - Cars, undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - Prints, 1944, undated (Folder 2)
    - Unidentified groups of soldiers with a jeep next to them and President Roosevelt?s message on the roadside board which reads, "There are many roads to Tokyo; we will neglect none of them,", undated (Folder 2: 8)
    - Thomas Dewey and an unidentified individual, undated (Folder 2: 9)
    - Soldiers in war ravaged areas, burial of dead soldiers on Omaha Beach and other Normandy beaches, tanks and planes, and Cherbourg after the surrender of Germany, 1944-1945 and undated (Folder 2: 10-12)
- Oversize File, circa 1940s, undated (Box Map File)
  Includes military maps of various parts of France, printed maps of France, Europe, and world maps, proclamations and other print memorabilia. In English and in French